This is the depths' second layer...
ここが 深界二層
We did it, Reg!
やったよレグ
We've survived our final lesson!
私達最後の授業の乗り切ったよ
そうなのか
Is that so?
Sure is!
そうだよ
リーダー 私達やったよ
Leader, we pulled it off!
It hasn't really hit me yet...
実感があんまりないんだが
Did we really get away from them?
僕らは本当に逃げ切れたのか
That's right!
そうだよ
We don't have to worry about anyone
pursuing us anymore!
もう追手を気にすることもないんだよ
Let's hurry on, Reg.
It might be calling all of its buddies over here.
急ごうレグ
仲間を呼んでるかも知れない
Yeah...
They must prepare themselves for what's to come.
覚悟しなければならない
In this place that transcends the ordinary,
they themselves are outsiders,
日常を踏み越えたこの地では
自分たちこそが遺物であり 敵であり エサであり 脅威なのだ
the enemy,
the prey...
They're a threat.
These leaves sure are huge...
大きな葉っぱだね
Yeah, and the smell of the greenery has gotten stronger.
ああ 緑の匂いも一段と濃くなったな
しかし 身を隠すのにはいいが
Also, while it's nice that the leaves help hide us,
they totally block the view of our surroundings.
丸っきり周りも見えないな
いいかいレグくん
Listen, Reg.
These trees might be big, but they're similar to amagiri.
この木は大きいけどアマギリの仲間なんだよ
"Amagiri"?
アマギリ
Right.
そう
Here, look!
ほら 見て見て
アマギリの新芽はね必ずアビスの北を向いてるの
Amagiri sprouts always point
toward the north of the Abyss...
同じようにね
just like these do.
The branches similarly always point
toward the center of the Abyss.
枝は必ずアビスの中心方向を向くんだよ
Oh...
So, they're helpful when it's hard
to make out your surroundings.
周りが見えない時は頼りになるから
遭難したらアマギリを辿れって昔から言われてるんだ
There's an old saying that goes:
"If you get lost, just follow the amagiri."
Whoa, you sound pretty smart right now, Riko...
なんだか賢く見えるぞ リコ
nothing like when we were back in Orth!
オースにいた時とは偉い違いだ
あれ 褒められてるんだよね
Wait... That's a compliment, right?
えっと ここから降りればいいんだよね
Let's see...
We're supposed to descend from around here, right?
We really need to head to Seeker Camp,
the monitoring base down here.
なるべく監視基地 シーカーキャンプ行かないと
Help me!
助けて
Somebody's voice? This isn't like that other time...
あの時とは違う
What's the matter?!
どうしたの
Shh! There's somebody here!
誰かいる
Help...
助けて
Over there!
あっちだ
Someone's crying for help!
助けを求めてる
ほんと
Really?!
Help...
助けて
聞こえた
I heard it!
Help...
助けて
倒れてるの 探窟家だ
Down on the ground there... It's a cave raider!
I'll drive that thing away.
僕が追い払おう
Help me... Help...
たすけて たすけ
レグ待って
Reg, hold on! It could be a trap!
罠かも知れない
罠
A trap?
That thing is a corpse-weeper...
あれ ナキカバネっていうの
獲物がたすけを呼ぶ声を真似して
They mimic the cries for help of prey they capture
to lure others to their colonies.
たすけ
コロニーに誘い込むの
だから あの人はもう
Which means... that person is already...
Reg, get down!
レグ 伏せて
Riko!
リコ
別のやつか 迂闊
Another one?! How careless of me!
大丈夫 まだ届く距離だ
It's okay.
It's... It's still in range!
Calm down...
落ち着け 絶対外すな
I can't miss this!
Everyone, unable to resist, goes down in
誰もが逆らえずに潜っていく
その目を灯火より輝かせて
Make those eyes shine brighter than a torch
The destination we are aiming for is deep
目指す先は深く まっすぐに迷い込む
We squarely lose our way
口開けた奈落の罠 真実の跡を追いかけよう
The trap of the open-mouthed netherworld
Let's chase the traces of truth
今答えが 見つかるなら 全部失くしてもいい
If an answer can be found now, we don't mind losing it all
その声を 離さないように 木霊がまだ響いてる
The echo is still reverberating
So that we do not part with that voice
羅針盤はずっと 闇を指したまま逃げ場のない 方へ
The compass is always
Pointed to the darkness
Where there is no escape
In that direction
それが呪いでも 鼓動は本物
Even if that is a curse
The pulse is the real thing
二度と憧れは 止まらない
Never again will the yearning stop
Incinerator
Reg!
レグ
This is bad!
まずい アビス内の上昇は
Ascending within the Abyss means...!
リコ
Riko!
遠い
Too far!
She's being fed to the chicks?!
雛の餌
No!
だめだ やめてくれ
D-don't do it!
No!
いやだ
リコ
Riko!
What...?
何か 何か手は
What can I possibly do?!
Where...?
どこに どこにいるんだ
Where am I...?
Go!
行け
Yet again.
まただ
But still, this feeling...
だがこの感覚は「身体が思い出した」
My body remembers.
In the past, I did something like this.
「かつて こうしたことがある」
Riko!
リコ
Ah... the strain of the second layer is serious.
二層に負荷は重い 早く降ろさないと
I need to lay her down quickly...
If that thing had hit Riko...
もし あれがリコに当たっていたら
What in the...
何なんだ 僕は一体 何なんだ
What in the world...
am I?
She doesn't seem to be injured.
怪我はないみたいだな
Reg...
レグ
Riko!
リコ よかったぁ
I'm glad you're awake!
You wouldn't wake up, so I got really worried!
なかなか目覚めないから心配したぞ
Ah, but... you should stay lying down for now...
ああ でもまだ起きない方が
Uh...
いや なかなか目覚めないから 怪我だったらどしようかと
You were taking so long to wake up,
so I thought you might be hurt...
And, uh...
その それに服も吐瀉物で汚れてて
And your clothes were all covered with vomit and stuff.
Oh, come on, Reg,
you don't need to act so embarrassed.
やだなぁレグ そんなに恥ずかしがらなくてもいいのに
You're a robot, after all.
ロボなんだし
Besides, you're the one who saved me, Reg, right?
それに助けてくれたのもレグなんでしょ
レグが
Reg, did...
Reg, did you...
レグが
Reg, did you do this?
レグがこれやったの
I kind of lost myself in the moment...
無我夢中だったんだが
But to think I ended up doing this...
まさかこんなことになるなんて
Amazing!
すごい
Hey, it must've come out of this spot on your hand here?
ねえねえやっぱりこの手のトコから出たの
I wonder what we should name it...
名前何がいいかな
インシネレーター
Incinerator! Let's call this cannon thing that!
「火葬砲」にしよっか
Uh, Riko...
リコ とてもそんな気分には
I'm not in the mood for this...
I very nearly completely blew you away.
危うく君ごと吹き飛ばす所だったんだ
If I had, I...
もし そうなったら僕は
Reg! It's alright!
レグ
大丈夫
Let's see, it was around...
ええとねだいたい
これぐらいだったよ
this big or so.
What exactly was?
一体何が
初めて私を助けてくれた時 レグが使った火葬砲の大きさだよ
The size of the blast from your Incinerator
the first time you saved me, Reg!
And that was from about 200 meters away!
それも大体200メートルも先から
大丈夫
It'll be fine!
Reg, you used to be able to control that power quite well!
レグはこの力を使いこなせていたんだ
一緒に特訓しよ
Let's train it together!
君はこの力を 使いこなせるんだよ
This power of yours...
is something you can master!
Riko...
リコ
Reg...?
レグ
Huh? What's going on?
あれ どうしたんだ
大丈夫 レグ
Are you alright? Reg?
Reg!
レグ
レグ どーしたんのレグ
What's the matter, Reg?!
Help...
助けて 助けて
Help me...
Gone... Gone...
ない ないよ
It's gone...
ないよ
It's gone!
Riko?
リコ
レグ 起きた
Reg, you're awake!
ねぇねぇねぇ大丈夫
Hey, so are you alright?
You suddenly fell asleep and
wouldn't wake up no matter what!
急に寝ちゃって全然起きないんだもん
火葬砲撃って疲れちゃった
Did firing your Incinerator tire you out?
Ah, that right...?
あぁ そうか
I'm, uh... fine.
その 大丈夫だ
I see! Good to hear!
そうか よかった
Anyway, what were you yelling about?
ところで 何を叫んでいたんだ
Oh, that's right!
そうなの
My cave-raiding notebook is gone!
私探窟手帳がなくなってるの
That notebook you were always making memos in?
いつもメモをとっていたあの手帳か
Yeah.
It's possible I dropped it
when that corpse-weeper snatched me...
ひょっとしたらナキカバネに掴まれた時落としちゃったかも
ポーチの留め具も壊されてたし
The clasp on my pouch also got busted.
If that's the case, then...
そうなると
Well, there's nothing we can do about it.
まっ しょうがないか
いいのかい
You okay with that?!
Yeah...
うん どうせなくすなら奈落の底まで行ってからが良かったけどね
but if I had to lose it, I would've liked to have gotten
to the bottom of the netherworld first...
I mean, when it's found a long time from now,
it'll only contain my writings up till this point,
だってさ
のちのち発見された時にここら辺の事までしか書いてなかったら
so my legend won't spread far and wide, you know?
私の伝説が轟かないじゃない
「すごい リコさんまじで最深部にたどり着いたんだ」とか
Stuff like: "Amazing! Riko totally made it
to the deepest depths!" Or...
"That Star Compass really was pointed
to the netherworld's bottom!" and so on.
「あの星の羅針盤も本当に奈落の底を指してたなんて」とか
But you dropped that not too long ago, too...
それもさっき落としたけどな
I at least wanted to add something about your Incinerator
to my catalog of your features, Reg.
せめてレグの機能大全に
「火葬砲」書き加えたかったなぁ
That's my only regret...
それだけが心残りだよ
たしか 僕のちんちんが生っぼいとかも書いてあったな
I'm quite sure she also wrote something in there about
how my penis looks like a real one...
I hope it stays hidden
in the netherworld's darkness for all eternity.
永久に奈落の闇に眠るといい
新しいの作ろう
Let's make a new one!
Oh!
I tried roasting it under some ouba leaves.
オウバの葉で蒸し焼きにしてみました
I kept the seasoning simple and only used rock salt
and ground-up Eternal Fortunes.
味付けはシンプルに岩塩とトコシエコウの実だけだよ
This... even looks tasty, doesn't it?!
これは 見た目まで美味しそうではないか
いただきます
Thanks for the food!
Yum! It's got a delicious taste
that appeals to the instincts!
本能に訴える旨さ
Riko! This is a bit peculiar but it's tasty!
リコ これは癖はあるけどうまい
On top of that, you did well
to kill some game on your own.
しかしよく一人で獲物を仕留めたれたな
これね レグが仕留めたナキカバネのお肉だよ
Actually, Reg, this is meat
from that corpse-weeper you killed.
その リコは 平気なのかい
Uh... Riko, that doesn't bother you?
Corpse-weepers sometimes eat humans, right?
ナキカバネは 人を食べてたりもするんだろう
In fact, we just witnessed...
現にさっき
うん そうだねぇ
That's true.
レグはロボットなのに気になるんだね
So, Reg, that still concerns you
despite being a robot, huh?
Y-yeah...
It's probably 'cause we both look generally the same...
自分と同じ形をしているせいだろうか
You know, we sometimes had meat
at the orphanage too, right?
孤児院でもさ たまにお肉出てきたよね
Yeah...
Well, most all of that stuff was hunted
by Blue Whistles in the first layer.
あれってね 深界一層で蒼笛達が狩って来たものが殆どなんだけど
Those kinds of primeval creatures also feed on
cave raiders and ruffians to some degree or other.
そういう原生生物は多かれ少なかれ探窟家とかならず者を食べているのよ
そうなのか
Is that so...?
It's sad when they die...
死んじゃうのは悲しいけど
彼らは生物の血肉になって それで再び私達の力になるの
But they become the flesh and blood of those creatures,
and then once again become our strength.
我々は 探窟家はそうやって強くなってきたのよ
That is how we - all us cave raiders - have grown strong.
I see...
そうか
Even that scene that revisited me in a nightmare
is just part of daily life down here...
悪夢にまで見たあの光景ですら
ここでは日々営みの一つに過ぎないのだ
All of the resilience of those who live here
was built up for the sake of life in the Abyss.
ここで生きる者たちの強かさの全ては
アビスに生きるために身につけたもの
This really is delicious...
やはりうまいな
Lowest Area of the Depths' Second Layer
Inverted Forest
It's the real thing...
本物だ
ほら 滝が上に向かって流れてる
Look!
The waterfalls are flowing upward!
Oh my...
真っ直ぐ飛ばないね
Seems it won't shoot straight.
The wind here is blowing like crazy.
風がめちゃくちゃに吹いているんだ
Guess we can't keep taking shortcuts like we have been.
今までのように近道はできないな
What's the matter, Riko?
どうしたリコ
なんか 冷えてきたかも
Uh, I feel like it somehow got colder...
I know it's windy, but...
風もそうなんだけど
Here in the Inverted Forest, I wonder if we
don't get that much light reflected by the force field.
逆さ森って あんま力場からの光が反射しないのかな
Seems pretty gloomy, right?
薄暗いよね
大丈夫か 防寒具を出そうか
You okay? Want me to get out the cold-weather gear?
Uh, nah, we can't spread out our supplies here,
so later's okay.
ううん ここじゃ荷物広げられないから 後で
Riko, hold this for a little bit.
リコ ちょっと持っていてくれ
It's warm!
あったかい
Try to make do with that until things settle down.
落ち着くまでそれで我慢してくれ
レグは寒くないの
Reg, you're not cold?
I can feel the wind, but no, not really.
風は感じるが特にには
I figured as much!
さすが
Well, I'll be borrowing this for now, then.
じゃあちょっと借りるね
Reg! Some kind of symbol appeared on your helmet!
レグ たまに何が印が出てる
Huh?
Wow...
I never noticed it before!
今まで気付かなかったよ
寝てる時は出てなかったよこれ
It never showed up while you were sleeping...
not even once!
What could it be?
なんだろ
レグノ故郷の文字なのかもね
Reg, maybe it's the writing system
they use where you come from.
Huh?
A-ah, it's disappearing!
消えちゃう
What are those...?
あれは
Um... I think they're called inbyos...
えっと インビョウかな
Looks like they're saying, "This is our turf."
「縄張りだぞ」って言ってるみたい
Think they're angry?
怒ってるのか
Here they come!
来た
リコ大丈夫か
Riko, you alright?
Y-yeah...
どうやら 縄張りから抜けたみたいだな
Seems we managed to make it out of their territory...
Hup!
You sure you're headed in the right direction?
方向はこっちでいいのか
Yep, we should be able to see the route
to the Seeker Camper soon.
うん もうすぐシーカーチャンプまでのルートが見えるはずだよ
言ったでしょ
I told you, right? I know where we're going.
ちゃんと覚えてるだから
お師様 お師様 なにか近づいてます
Master! Master!
Something's approaching.
二人です 一人は赤笛なのですか
It's two people.
One's a Red Whistle... and the other one...
もう一人が 探窟家ですらないような
doesn't even seem to be a cave raider...
Shall I ready the gondola?
ゴンドラの準備は
お師様
Master...?
I get the feeling the wind's calmed down.
なんだか 風が穏やかだな
That might be because we've left
the central part of the Abyss.
アビスの中心から離れてきたからかも
Come to think of it, the creatures here
are more peaceful, too.
そういや 生き物も大人しいよね
So that's how it works?
そういうものなのか
力場がね 光とか栄養とか運ぶから
The force field, you see, carries light and nutrients,
so there are more creatures
the closer you get to the central shaft.
縦穴に近い程生き物が多いんだって
そこから離れれば 呪いもちょっとはマシになるって言われてるよ
I also hear that when you get farther away from there
the Curse becomes a bit more bearable.
シーカーキャンプが妙に離れた場所にあるのもそう言う理由か
So that's why the Seeker Camp is in
such a strangely remote place, huh?
Well, you see...
えーっとね
The Inverted Forest is too high up
to descend from directly,
元々逆さ森が高すぎて降りられないから
so it was originally built as a stopover point
for people taking the long way around.
迂回するために作った中継地点なの
It just so happened that the location proved convenient.
そしたらたまたま都合がよかったんだって
Like, long-range visibility is better
where the force field is weak, right?
ほら 力場が弱いと遠くまで見通しが利くでしょ
So they ended up constructing a large telescope there.
それで大きな望遠鏡を作ってね
Riko...
リコ
Is that...
あれ 望遠鏡か
the telescope?
Wow!
So this is the Seeker Camp, huh?
これが シーカーキャンプ
It's really quite high up there...
随分高いところにあるんだな
あれ そういえば
Huh? Speaking of that...
What's wrong?
どうしたんだ
Um, well...
うん ええとね
I heard the Seeker Camp always has a lookout on duty.
シーカーキャンプには いつも見張りさんがいるんだって
So when someone starts approaching,
I was told they lower the gondola for them...
だから 近づくだけでゴンドラ下ろしてくれるって聞いたんだけど
赤笛に ロボット
A Red Whistle... A robot...
警戒されているかもしれないな
They might be feeling wary...
レグ あそこまでて伸ばせる
Reg, are you able to stretch your arm up there?
Maybe with both arms, or...
両手なら或いは
やってみよう
Let's give it a try.
なんとか届き
Seems I managed to re-
レグ どうしたの
Reg, what's wrong?
Something has...
何かに 腕を 掴まれた
grabbed...
my arms.
Huh?!
So she's still alive... that brat.
まだ生きてたんだ あのガキ
The Unmovable Sovereign, Ozen the Immovable...
「不動卿」動かざるオーゼン
a White Whistle who possesses
unrivaled physical strength.
無双の怪力を持つ白笛
その目に宿る光は
That glint in her eyes...
子供達にとって 希望の光か それとも不吉の前兆か
For these children, will it prove to be a glint of hope?
Or is it instead an ominous omen?
The glittering waves that float in the sky
空に浮かんでる光る波を束ねて虹の橋をかけよう
Let's bundle them and build a rainbow bridge
危うい足場 滑るスロープ
A dangerous foothold, a slope we slide on
過去と未来の道標
A signpost of the past and future
君の左手 僕の右手を
Your left hand, with my right hand
Join it, connect us, and let's begin
繫いで繫げてはじめよう
いつも そばに いるよ
I am always beside you
過去も 今も 未来も
In the past, the present, and also the future
だから迷わずに歩いていこう
So let's walk along without hesitating
色とりどりの夢 重ねて
Pile up multicolored dreams
明日はどこに向かう
Where will we head toward tomorrow?
君と一緒にいれたら 世界は輝きだすよ
If I can be together with you, the world will begin to shine
最果ての地に咲く花を探そう
Let's search for flowers that bloom at the ends of the earth
Next Episode
Seeker Camp